A Guide to the Records of John M. Gandy
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
A Guide to the Records of John M. Gandy 1916-1946
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
VSU RG 2/3
7 Boxes
Transfered to the Archives
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Manuel Gandy was appointed the third president of the Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute, after the death of James Hugo Johnston in 1914. His teaching career began in Stone County Mississippi, and he also taught briefly in Hanson, Oklahoma before attending Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee. While a student at Fisk he taught at various schools in Tennessee and Kentucky. In 1898 he was appointed to the position of professor of Greek and Latin at Virginia Normal and Collegiate Institute, now (Virginia State University). When the College program was terminated in 1902 by the State he continued as professor of education until he was appointed president of the University in 1914.
As president he oversaw the schools development which included becoming the "Land Grant College" for blacks in Virginia in 1920. He also worked to have the college department returned to the University in 1923. Gandy also saw the renaming of the V N and II to Virginia State College for Negroes and the establishment of the graduate school 1937. The return of the college department in 1923 and the renaming of the V.N. and I.I. to Virginia State College for Negroes in1930 and the establishment of the graduate school in 1937.
While President of the University, John Gandy was very active in a number of organizations. A few of the organizations Mr. Gandy was involved with are as follows: he was President of the Association of Presidents of Negro Land Grant Colleges, President of the Virginia State Teachers Association, and President of the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools. He was also a member of several boards and a member of the Board of Trustees of Virginia Union University in Richmond, Virginia, and on the board of the "Negro Organizational."
He served as President of Virginia State University until he retired in 1943 and as President Emeritus until his death in 1947.
Scope and Content Information
Mr. Gandy's correspondence shows just how involved College Presidents at this time were in the day to day operation of the University. The subjects range from the Governors office to individual students and family members.
Contents List
- Annual Reports
  - 1914-1915 (Box-folder 01:1)
  - 1915-1916 (Box-folder 01:2)
  - 1916-1917 (Box-folder 01:3)
  - 1917-1918 (Box-folder 01:4)
  - 1919-1920 (Box-folder 01:5)
  - 1920-1921 (Box-folder 01:6)
  - 1921-1922 (Box-folder 01:7)
  - 1922-1923 (Box-folder 01:8)
  - 1923-1924 (Box-folder 01:9)
  - 1924-1925 (Box-folder 01:10)
  - 1925-1926 (Box-folder 01:11)
  - 1926-1927 (Box-folder 01:12)
  - 1927-1928 (Box-folder 01:13)
  - 1928-1929 (Box-folder 01:14)
  - 1930-1931 (Box-folder 01:15)
  - 1932-1933 (Box-folder 01:16)
  - 1933-1934 (Box-folder 01:17)
  - 1934-1935 (Box-folder 01:18)
  - 1935-1936 (Box-folder 01:19)
  - 1936-1937 (Box-folder 01:20)
  - 1937-1938 (Box-folder 01:21)
  - 1938-1939 (Box-folder 01:22)
  - 1931 (Box-folder 01:23)
  - 1940-1941 (Box-folder 01:24)
- General Correspondence
  - 1916-1918 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - 1919 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1920 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 1921 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 1922-1923 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1922 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - 1922 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - 1923 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1924 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - 1925-1926 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - 1928 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - 1935 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - 1935-1937 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - 1938-1940 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - 1932-1937 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - 1946 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - 1927-1930 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1931-1932 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 1932 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Jan-June 1933 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - July-October 1933 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Nov-Dec 1933 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Jan-March 1934 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - General Correspondence July-Sept 1934 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Oct-Dec 1934 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Jan-March 1935 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - June-July 1935 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Aug-Sept 1935 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Oct-Dec 1935 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Jan-Feb 1936 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - March-April 1936 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - July-Aug 1936 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - May-June 1936 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - General Correspondence Sept-Oct 1936 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - November 1936 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - December 1936 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - January 1937 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - February 1937 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - March 1937 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - April 1937 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - May 1937 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - June 1937 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - July-Aug 1937 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Sept-Oct 1937 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Nov-Dec 1937 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Jan-Feb 1938 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - March-April 1938 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - May-June 1938 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - July-Aug 1938 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Sept 1938 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - May-Aug 1938 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Sept-Dec 1940 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Jan-Feb 1941 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - March-April 1941 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - General Correspondence May-June 1941 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - General Correspondence July-Aug 1941 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - General Correspondence Sept-Oct 1941 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - General Correspondence Nov-Dec 1941 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - General Correspondence Jan-March 1942 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - General Correspondence April 1942 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - General Correspondence May 1942 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - General Correspondence June 1942 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Budget 1935-1936 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Dining Hall Committee 1933 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Gandy Publications (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Papers (Presentations) 1920 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Paper-"Redeeming a Race Through It's Children" 1922 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Paper-"Emancipation Day"- Negro Press 1925 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Paper-"Presidnets Address"-VTA 1926 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Paper-"Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute, the College for Negro Youth" for the Governer (Capital Outlay) 1925-1926 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Papers-Baccalaureeate Speece (VSU) Formal Opening 1927 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Paper-"The Objective of the Negro College" (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Paper-"Library of the Negro College" (Box-folder 4:20)
  - News Clipping (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Flyer-Hi Y Conference (Box-folder 4:22)
  - Flyer- Highpoints (Box-folder 4:23)
  - Covers-Southern Workman 1908-1927 (Box-folder 4:24)
  - Minutes- Desirable Extension 1941 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Committee-"Negro Graduate Education Report" 1935 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Committee Commencement 1940 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Commitee Disassan Groups (Box-folder 5:4)
  - VSU-Regulations 1929-1932 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Report-Student Activity Fund 1933-1936 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Report-Annual Salary (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Division Recommendations 1937-1938 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Department of Business Report (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Bill-Retirement Report (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Senior Women Request (College) (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Student Constitution ca. 1934-1935 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - University Calender 1936-1937 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Proposed Constitution 1935 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Proposed to transfer to Norfolk District to VSU (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Allen,Ada 1/6/1917 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Anthony, R.I. 8/1/1918 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Anderson, Mattye 1/8/1917 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Baer, Jamie 1/5/1917 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Brown,Howard 7/21/1918 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Bryant, William 8/15/1918 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Butler, Nannie 2/10/1917 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Burton, S.B. 8/19/1919 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Cater, Cecyl 4/14/1917 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Christbrugh, D. Harriet 7/25/1918 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Coleman, Elizabeth 12/18/1916 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Coleman, Margaret 12/11/1916 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Cooper, Erlena 7/9/1918 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Cooper, Stewart 7/12/1917 (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Dangerfield, A. Gertrude 1/24/1917 (Box-folder 6:15)
  - Cordery,Roy 7/9/1918 (Box-folder 6:16)
  - Day,Grace 6/6/1918 (Box-folder 6:17)
  - Forrester,Joseph 3/5/1917 (Box-folder 6:18)
  - Fowlkes, Maude 4/1/1917 (Box-folder 6:19)
  - Graham, Odette 1/5/1917 (Box-folder 6:20)
  - Gulley, Elizabeth 1/9/1917 (Box-folder 6:21)
  - Hall, Gertrude 8/1/1917 (Box-folder 6:22)
  - Hayes, Marion 5/23/1917 (Box-folder 6:23)
  - Hodges, Cora 2/2/1917 (Box-folder 6:24)
  - Hough, F. Harrison 3/14/1917 (Box-folder 6:25)
  - Hubert, Emma 1/4/1917 (Box-folder 6:26)
  - Jackson,Miriam 7/31/1918 (Box-folder 6:27)
  - Jones, Maud 2/25/1917 (Box-folder 6:28)
  - Johnson, Irene 5/4/1918 (Box-folder 6:29)
  - Johnson, Jaime 6/4/1917 (Box-folder 6:30)
  - Johnson, R.S. 4/27/1917 (Box-folder 6:31)
  - Key, Raymond G. 5/21/1918 (Box-folder 6:32)
  - Lattimer, Lillian 7/15/1918 (Box-folder 6:33)
  - Lawrence, Lillian 6/19/1917 (Box-folder 6:34)
  - King, W.L.G. 7/15/1918 (Box-folder 6:35)
  - Madison, Authur 11/17/1917 (Box-folder 6:36)
  - Martin,Sadye 7/9/1918 (Box-folder 3:37)
  - McDaniel, Harriet 3/12/1917 (Box-folder 6:38)
  - Moore, Lillian M.D. 8/10/1917 (Box-folder 6:39)
  - Morrow, D. Lane 5/19/1917 (Box-folder 6:40)
  - Murry, E.M. 3/1/1917 (Box-folder 6:41)
  - Nutt, Etna 5/31/1917 (Box-folder 6:42)
  - Pettyjohn, Alice 8/21/1917 (Box-folder 6:43)
  - Philips, Rachel 8/5/1918 (Box-folder 6:44)
  - Porter, Coma 2/13/1917 (Box-folder 6:45)
  - Practer, J.B. 9/12/1918 (Box-folder 6:46)
  - Plummer, Mildred 12/18/1916 (Box-folder 6:47)
  - Riddle, H.T. 6/18/1917 (Box-folder 6:48)
  - Roane, Theodore 7/12/1917 (Box-folder 6:49)
  - Robertson, C.B 12/15/1916 (Box-folder 6:50)
  - Saxon, Mary 7/22/1918 (Box-folder 6:51)
  - Seldon, John 7/8/1918 (Box-folder 6:52)
  - Smith, Harriet 8/6/1918 (Box-folder 6:53)
  - Smith, Jessie 6/8/1918 (Box-folder 6:54)
  - Smith, Myra W. 5/22/1917 (Box-folder 6:55)
  - Smith, Zenobia 1/15/1914 (Box-folder 6:56)
  - Taylor, Elsie 7/3/1918 (Box-folder 6:57)
  - Turfley, Pearl 3/15/1917 (Box-folder 6:58)
  - Usher, S.C. 9/28/1918 (Box-folder 6:59)
  - Watson, Jennie 5/15/1917 (Box-folder 6:60)
  - Watts, Robert 7/20/1918 (Box-folder 6:61)
  - Woodson, Sarah 7/9/1918 (Box-folder 6:62)
  - Job Specifications (Box-folder 6:63)